The good news is the IRS is reporting a
10% increase in the size of the average
taxpayer refund and how more taxpayers
are getting it. However, initial data
also shows Americans are not spending
the windfall. Instead, understandably,
they're either saving the money or using
the proceeds to pay down debt. Now, both
of those things are positive in their
own right, helping struggling Americans
after years of forgot how to grow in
flat beverage, but from the broader
economic perspective, this is not what
people were hoping for. It is what
should have been expected though,
particularly in the context of basic
economic small e economics, not the
stuff that's preached by PhD capital
economists who tout the macroeconomic
benefits from government stimulus. We've
seen this before in 2008 as well as 2001
with very similar results. Repeated
experience shows that when people are
under stress, they behave rationally,
even prudently. In that sense, the lack
of spending is just another sign of the
tremendous strain that everybody's
under. And while even while the refunds
are ramping up in January and February
this year, the Federal Reserve's
consumer credit data had already
indicated growing caution well before
the Iran conflict and energy shock. The
aggregate revolving credit balance
across the banking system was flat. And
since these credit estimates correspond
very clearly with jobs data, including
the payroll numbers, at least, you know,
after they have been revised to better
reflect the length and the depth of the
ongoing flat beverage employment
weakness, that was an early warning
about how Americans would respond, or in
this case, not respond as had been
hoped. After all, with the jobs market
and therefore incomes contracting in the
second half of last year, and again to
start this year, workers, consumers,
they've already been falling further and
further behind.
Toss in the $4 price of gasoline and
what happens is what everybody should
have expected to happen. Americans use
the money, the tax refunds that they're
getting, that's a positive, but they're
using the refunds not to spend, but to
pay down debt and to save for the
future. And where it does get spent,
unfortunately, it's being spent on that
$4 gasoline.
So again, the good news is the tax cuts
are producing more refunds, more money
in the hands of taxpayers is always
always a positive. But as far as
macroeconomic stimulus, the results are
always underwhelming whenever the
economy is facing substantial headwinds.
When it's on a downturn, it's the
downturn that matters, not the stimulus.
Now, we know that's been the case the
last couple years because for one thing,
American consumers have been telling us
that non-stop. Consumer sentiment has
deteriorated sharply across every
survey, not just the most extreme ones
like the University of Michigan's. It
goes back to 2024 when employment really
started to drop off and flat beverage
began to show up. Lack of jobs, lack of
incomes, higher cost of living forced on
the world years ago. People outside the
top income tiers, they've been falling
further and further behind. Their debts
become a bigger burden, which is in fact
the primary reason why we got to know
the cockroaches, for example, like
Tricolor. It was stressed subprime
households who just couldn't take
flagging incomes and the lack of jobs
any longer. Many started to buckle, and
when they did, it started to pull back
the curtain on the insanity and garbage
in private credit. But from the start,
tax refunds, okay, good idea for
individuals, just don't expect it to
produce a broader positive effect on
spending. Remember, that's what
economists, the capital E variety,
constantly claim. You give people money,
they spend it, which leads to more
revenue for businesses, which then hire
more workers who now have more income so
they can spend more and so on into the
theoretical virtuous circle of
Keynesianism.
But if stressed workers don't spend
their tax refunds, the circle doesn't
get closed and the economy doesn't pick
up even if the government is throwing
around the big bucks to do so. As we'll
see in a minute, that's exactly what
happened the last couple of times this
was tried under these similar
circumstances. Paying down debt, saving
money, at best in this case spending on
higher gasoline but little else. And
that's what the initial data here in
2026 is already showing. In a world
where markets swing on every headline,
focus matters. That's why Euro Dollar
University offers its one big weekly
theme, a disciplined thematic analysis
that you can count on.
If you don't have time to go all the way
to the depth of Euro Dollar University's
comprehensive deep dive analysis, but
you want to get the next best thing, one
big weekly theme is for you. Each week
we pick the one high impact macro and
market theme and we unpack it from first
principles, from fundamentals to real
world implications, so you can see the
forest and the trees, drawing from all
over the vast Euro Dollar University
library and canon. What you get with one
big weekly theme is a single focus theme
each week unpacked with clarity from
sources you will not see anywhere else.
Data driven analysis supported by charts
and information pulled from Euro Dollar
University's other subscriptions and
offerings. All in a simple, repeatable
framework you'll use week after week.
We distill the complexity into a
practical fundamentals first playbook
that you can rely on. This is not about
chasing every hot idea. It's about
building a disciplined routine that
sharpens your judgment during these
periods of uncertainty. So if you're
ready to make your week count, subscribe
to one big weekly theme today. Visit
eurodollaruniversity.substack.com
or click the link in the description to
learn more. You can sample the service
or sign up and get started straight
away.
Euro dollar university, a focused
approach to mastering money and macro
one thoughtful week at a time.
End quote.
Federal refunds are averaging about
$3,500 this year according to the
Internal Revenue Service data through
early April. That's up roughly 350 bucks
or about 10% from last spring thanks to
tax changes in President Donald Trump's
one big beautiful bill act. Many
households are using the extra cash to
shore up their finances rather than
splurge. At a time of they say stubborn
inflation it's really lack of income and
soaring gas prices from the Iran war,
they're focused on getting their own
fiscal homes in order. Early tax filers
increased their debt payments by about
20% in the 3 weeks after receiving
refunds. 20% increase in debt
repayments. According to David Tinsley,
the senior economist at the Bank of
America Institute. That includes paying
down student loans, that's a big one, as
well as car and credit card balances.
And lower income households, those who
are pinched the most by the
affordability crisis, again lack of
income, they're just different terms for
lack of income.
Have put even more of their refunds,
nearly 30%, into repaying debts. They're
also using the refunds to catch up on
other bills. Some are maybe buying
clothes, phones and other personal items
for themselves or their families, but
only after taking care of necessities.
As Tinsley himself says, they're not
just rushing out and blowing these
refunds, they're also repairing their
balance sheets.
That last little bit was already on
display in February before we got to the
energy shock, the Iran conflict and $4
gasoline. Americans had already been
paying down or at least not taking out
as many credit cards and credit card
balances as they had been. Revolving
consumer credit according to the Federal
Reserve has been getting weaker and
weaker and weaker in the same manner as
the job market. Unlike installment loans
for cars or appliances, which are more
related to changes in interests,
credit card use tends to correlate with
employment. Whenever card owners are
secure in their jobs and confident about
their incomes and opportunities for
better income, they'll naturally run up
their revolving debts. However, once
they begin to sense labor market
softness, consumers begin to rethink
their usage. And should that softness
become, you know, flat beverage, they'll
put their cards away entirely. And the
further down the flat part of the
beverage curve we go, the more likely
borrowers actually pay down their
outstanding balances rather than take on
any additional ones. Consumers cut back
on their cards while also taking out
fewer new ones. The aggregate revolving
credit balance slows to a crawl and then
can even reverse the more jobs that get
lost. Now, what the Fed data showed for
February was a minuscule increase in the
seasonally adjusted balance. January
wasn't all that much either, and while
December was something of a splurge that
happens every now and again, card usage
has been clearly slowing down for some
time. Like I said in the intro, that
corresponds strongly with the
establishment survey data because, of
course, it does.
It's basic economics. So, that already
indicated how taxpayers, especially at
the bottom ends of the income spectrum,
were likely to be using their refunds
once they got them. They were paying
down credit cards before the refunds,
they're not going to stop now with them.
Because the labor market is anything
other than strong or solid, the
propensity to pay down debt is far
higher than it would be under better,
actually resilient employment
conditions. Consumers themselves,
they've said they're afraid on jobs and
income, they've been saying this more
strenuously for many, many months now,
for well over a year. So, the credit
data showed they were already behaving
that way. Tax refunds are just following
along the basic economics of reality.
Now, bumping up tax refunds, nothing
new. Governments have been using their
tax policies, largely tax cuts, as
stimulus forever, at least during this
Keynesian age. The results never good.
Same thing as with, you know, the
Federal Reserve and its rate cuts and
the other programs that they label
stimulus as well. At best, what you get
is economists standing there scratching
their head after it's over with and they
don't get the results that they
promised, instead saying, "Well, it
probably would have been worse if we did
nothing."
So, they end up arguing over how many
theoretical jobs they saved, rather than
any straightforward results which showed
the policy worked as it was intended.
Remember, giving taxpayers more of their
money, they're supposed to spend it
leading to the virtuous circle. Spending
leads to higher employment, which
creates more income, therefore more
spending, and so on. Now, it's a
questionable proposition, even in the
best of times, because research has long
showed people respond very differently
to windfalls than they do regular
income. Milton Friedman called it the
permanent income hypothesis, and it
doesn't really need a fancy name. Again,
this is just common sense, basic small e
economics. So, if you find $350 sitting
on the side of the road, you don't go
out and buy a new car or lock yourself
into that kind of payment. Maybe you
spend some of it, but based on macro
conditions, time and again history shows
you're far more likely to pay off the
bills you owe or pay down debt. Now, the
twin Bush experiments provide useful
examples. Now, people forget these
happened because that's how effective
they were. They were forgettable. No
virtuous circles, just more government
debt because good Dr. Keynes, he
demanded governments borrow to get the
economy rolling toward that circle, and
it never really happens. If you don't
remember early 2008, the Bush
administration's genius plan was to pay
off taxpayers with tax credits,
basically what most people imagine as
helicopter money. The Economic Stimulus
Act of 2008 was passed on February 13th
and 2/3 of that 150 billion that was
allocated for it, which was an enormous
amount for the time. It seems like a
drop in the bucket these days, but that
was enormous in early 2008. About 100
billion of it was these credits, literal
checks that were mailed directly to
taxpayers. Roughly 130 million
households received them, individuals.
They got between $300 and $600 while
joint filers ended up with between 6 and
1200. So, somewhat comparable to what
we're getting here in 2026. And what the
research shows is that the majority of
recipients, they paid down their debt,
they paid off their bills, and just
saved what was left over. And remember,
this wasn't late 2008. This was well
before Lehman Brothers. The economy was
in recession in effect, but most people
didn't know it. The labor market was
increasingly rough, and that's what they
were responding to, not the headlines
which continued to be positive,
especially anything that was said by any
central banker anywhere. The mainstream
said 2008, early 2008 anyway, was just a
little hiccup, and that the government
payments on top of the Fed's ridiculous
rate cuts would ensure the economy
wouldn't get any worse. It was supposed
to be a combination of fiscal, monetary,
it's not monetary, but fiscal and
Federal Reserve stimulus. Now, one of
the most widely cited studies on the
matter, the fiscal part of it, which
published in 2009, reported, quote,
"Only 1/5 of survey respondents said the
2008 tax rebates would lead them to
mostly increase spending. Most
respondents said they would either
mostly save the rebate or mostly use it
to pay off debt. The most common plan
for the rebate was debt repayment. The
survey estimates imply that the marginal
propensity to spend from the rebate was
about 1/3, and that there would not be
substantially more spending as a lagged
effect of the rebates." And that's part
of the Keynesianism, too. Spending leads
to more spending, which leads to more
spending. That didn't happen. And
because of low spending propensity, the
rebates in 2008 provided low, quote,
bang for the buck as economic stimulus.
And let me read that again. Because of
the low spending propensity, the rebates
in 2008 provided low bang for the buck
as economic stimulus. Putting cash into
the hands of consumers who use it to
save or pay off debt boost their
well-being, and that's not nothing, but
it does not necessarily make them spend.
In particular, low-income individuals
were particularly likely to use the
rebate to pay off debt. And we're seeing
exactly the same things here in 2026.
Now, this didn't mean, and it won't
mean, there there was no spending or
won't be spending nor any impact on the
economy. There was some, just as the
authors also write in the study, just a
lot less bang for the buck. GDP in the
second quarter of 2008, for example, it
turned positive after an ugly start to
the year. But it didn't make any
difference. It didn't stimulate a
turnaround. Uncle Sam went deeper into
debt so that individual taxpayers could
pay off some of their credit card bills.
You can see this in the savings rate for
2008. It jumped from 2.4% in April to
6.8% the next month in May as the checks
were being mailed and processed. But
after that, the savings rate dropped
back toward 3% again, not because
taxpayers began to spend, but because
what they feared would happen started to
happen. Incomes dropped even more as job
losses picked up more more and flatter
beverage. Now, the same study that I
just quoted also looked back at the 2001
experience because apparently George
Bush loved doing this mailing checks and
direct payment stuff. And guess what?
Very similar results. Most people back
then saved or paid down their debts.
Very small proclivity to spend. The
savings rate also spiked during the
summer 2001 when the stimulus checks
were being sent out. But because the
2001's dot-com recession was mild, many
economists thought these payments along
with, you know, Alan Greenspan's
aggressive rate cuts, they thought that
the combination of central bank policy
and fiscal policy had worked. They
hadn't stopped the recession, of course.
They didn't stop the job losses, but
maybe, they claim, it would have been
worse had authorities done nothing.
There was some jobs that were saved. A
counterfactual that no one can ever
disprove, which is kind of the point.
The stimulus didn't stimulate, so they
just say it did and claim that we know
it must have because it didn't get as
bad as 1929. Economics really is not a
serious discipline. It's an ideology
masquerading as a science. And the
counterpoint to this is, of course, 2020
and 2021. Bigger helicopter payments.
What seemed to be a much more direct and
obvious effect, certainly in consumer
prices, right?
First Trump twice, and then Biden sent
out even larger payments, this time
digitally dropped right on into
everybody's bank accounts, just to make
it convenient. Now, spending did
respond, but the evidence shows it
wasn't any more proportionally than 2001
or 2008. People still paid down debts
and saved. It appeared to have a bigger
impact. It appeared to have a bigger
impact, certainly on prices, because of
the unique circumstances of the time.
The lockdowns, the restraints, an
economy that was coming back off the
lows. It was already on its way up, not
falling further down as in 2001 and
2008. Plus, the price impact of what
everybody calls inflation was mainly
about the supply restrictions more than
the spending impact of government
payments. I mean, just look at the
savings rate. It shot up to a ridiculous
30% in April 2020, partly because there
was no spending or anything happening at
all, but it was still double digits
heading into 2021 before the third
helicopter from Biden pushed it way back
up to 26% all over again. Either way,
the more important variable is the state
of the labor market. It was on its way
back up five years ago, even if it
wouldn't get all the way there.
Meanwhile, in 2001 and 2008, consumers
were responding to employment, which was
moving further down the flat part of the
beverage curve, rather than climbing out
of it. And that's where we are in 2026,
going further flat. So, no surprise the
tax refund stimulus is not stimulating
as it had been hoped. The Keynesians are
Keynesing themselves all over again.
Remember, the primary purpose here,
according to economists, is to get
everything moving, to use the government
as the only game in town to restart
everything, or what Keynes himself
called pump priming. You throw some
money at the economy, it leads to
activity that then generates more
activity, and pretty soon you know it,
the whole thing is moving, the virtuous
circle.
That's just never how it works.
When the system is slowing down and
experiencing a downturn, stimulus does
not stop the downturn. The government
injections don't turn it around. At
best,
they have to claim that after it fails,
maybe it kept the downturn from being
worse than it otherwise would have
gotten to be without the stimulus that
didn't stimulate. Just look at China. By
all accounts, the current economy and
labor market remains firmly in a
downturn. I mean, the establishment
survey shows it. The income data does,
too. We went over revolving credit,
jolts, and the ugly jolts in hiring,
negative turnover there, consumer
sentiment across all the consumer
surveys. In other words, an entire array
of different kinds of evidence put
together by a variety of different
sources, and all of it says downturn.
Now, much of it points to a modest
contraction already, and one that was
not provoked by tariffs or tariff
uncertainty. It's much deeper than that,
and all the data shows it goes back much
farther. This thing has been slowly
grinding downward since early to
mid-2024.
In fact, the whole point behind the tax
cuts and refunds here in 2026
is the Trump administration figuring out
the economy really was in bad shape last
year and it actually had been getting
worse. Just look at the establishment
survey. Zero job growth for an entire
year in 2025. It really doesn't get much
worse than that except for the kinds of
recession that the NBR will even admit
is a recession. The tax cuts were
intended to be stimulus to try to solve
that problem, but it should be no
surprise that the results that we're
already getting are nearly identical to
the past rounds of stimulus which also
did not stimulate. And that's before we
even consider the the effect of higher
gasoline and the full weight of the
energy shock.
So on individual merits, yes, we should
always be looking to cut taxes, always.
Now it would be much better if lower
taxes were paired with significantly
lower spending, but that's just not the
world that we live in. It's also a big
positive for individuals, especially
households, because let's face it, they
need more help especially since the
economy sucks and it has sucked for
years. Jobs are disappearing, incomes
are not growing, in fact, they're
shrinking in relative terms. But as far
as stimulating the economy via spending,
it's not happening. Yes, there's going
to be some additional money spent in the
short run, but it'll be nowhere near
enough to change the trajectory of the
economy. Instead, the fact that
taxpayers aren't responding except in
the same way they always do under these
circumstances just further proves these
circumstances. You save money and pay
down debt when you're worried about jobs
and incomes and right now people are
saving money and paying down debt
because there's every reason for them to
be worried. Flat beverage rules the
game, not government checks.
And then when you start to add the
energy shock on top of all that, it
really starts to get to what the IMF
said was drifting closer to their
adverse scenario. All the details in the
video link below. As always, thank you
very much for joining me. Huge thank you
to all of you University members and
subscribers and until next time.
Take care.